A Guide to the Records of the Virginia War Memorial Commission, 1953-1983
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia War Memorial Commission, 1953-1983
The Library of Virginia
33938
4.05 cu. ft. (9 boxes)
Virginia. War Memorial Commission.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to architectural and engineering plans and drawings of current governmental buildings requires a written request from the prospective user and written authorization from the appropriate authority within the agency occupying the facility. See Archives staff for further information.
Acquisition Information
Transferred at an unknown date by the Dept. of Historic Resources, Richmond, Va.
Biographical Information
Created by an Act of the General Assembly (Chapter 244) in 1950, the Virginia World War II Memorial Commission was authorized to erect a World War II Memorial building to honor those Virginians who had served in World War II. The Commission, composed of fourteen members (five from the House of Delegates appointed by the Speaker of the House, four Senators appointed by the President of the Senate; four citizens-at-large appointed by the Governor; and the Adjutant General of Virginia), acts as the official custodian of the Memorial.
In 1979, the original Act was amended (Chapter 300) to honor not only the servicemen of World War II but also those of all modern wars. The name of the Commission was changed to the Virginia War Memorial Commission and its membership increased to include five citizens-at-large.
In 1984, the Act was repealed (Chapter 750). The Commission was put under the auspices of the Department of Conservation and Historic Resources. The composition of the Commission remained the same and its function as the custodian of the Memorial remained the same. In addition, the Commission was to participate with the Department, the U.S. military, and recognized veterans organizations in the planning, development, and execution of appropriate events that furthered the purposes of Chapter 750.
In 1985, the Legislature changed the name of the Commission to the Virginia War Memorial Board (Chapter 448). Its composition and function remained the same. When the Department of Conservation and Historic Resources reorganized in 1989, the Board was placed under the Department of Historic Resources (formerly the Division of Historic Landmarks within the Department).
The Virginia War Memorial building, located in Richmond, is an open marble and glass structure with the names of the war dead from World War II, the Korean War, and the Vietnam War etched into the walls. A marble statue sculpted by Leo Friedlander and entitled "Memory" stands at one end of the structure. At its base burns a "Torch of Liberty." Relics of various battle sites lie embedded in the floor of the Memorial. Designed by the architectural firm of T.J. Collins and Son of Staunton, Virginia, and built by the Thorington Construction Company, the Virginia War Memorial was dedicated on February 29, 1956. Subsequently, a Vietnam Wing, designed by the architectural firm of Ballou and Justice of Richmond, and constructed by Taylor and Parrish, Inc. of Richmond, was dedicated on November 20, 1981.
Civic, patriotic, and education groups may use the Memorial's small auditorium. Applications for use are reviewed by the Department of Historic Resources which then issues permits for use. The Capitol Police provide security for the Memorial and the Department of Buildings and Grounds provides grounds keeping and maintenance at the Memorial.
Scope and Content
Records, 1953-1983, of the Virginia War Memorial Commission.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Architectural drawings [restricted], ca. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biennial report, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Blueprints [restricted], ca. 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Chairfund, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Competition for memorial, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Construction records, 1953-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1977 January-June (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1977 July-December (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1978 January-June (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1978 July-December (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1981 January-June (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1981 July-December (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Vietnam Wing Dedication, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Insurance records, 1956-1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Mailing list, ca. 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Mechanical specifications, nd (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Pamphlets, postcards, etc., ca. 1950-1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Permits and applications, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Permits and applications, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Permits and applications, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Permits and applications, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Permits and applications, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Permits and applications, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Permits and applications, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Permits and applications, 1970 January-June (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Permits and applications, 1970 July-December (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Permits and applications, 1971 January-February (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Permits and applications, 1971 March-July (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Permits and applications, 1971 August-December (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Permits and applications, 1972 January-February (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Permits and applications, 1972 March-August (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Permits and applications, 1972 September-December (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Permits and applications, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Permits and applications, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Permits and applications, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Permits and applications, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Permits and applications, 1977 January-June (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Permits and applications, 1977 July-December (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Permits and applications, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Permits and applications, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Permits and applications, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Permits and applications, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Permits and applications, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Photographs, Misc., ca. 1960-1970 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Poem, nd (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Publicity, 1961-1978 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Requests for proposals, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Certificate of recognition, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence, 1982 June-September (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence 1982 October (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence 1982 November-December (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence, A-B, 1982 December (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence, C-D, 1982 December (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence, E-G, 1982 December (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence, H-K, 1982 December (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence, L-M, 1982 December (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence, N-S, 1982 December (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence, T-Z, 1982 December (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Correspondence, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Financial records, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Insignia, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Lists of participants, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Lists of organizations, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, List of Vietnam KIA from Virginia, nd (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Photographs, Negatives, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Photographs, Black and white, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Photographs, Color, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Programs, pamphlets, etc., ca. 1980 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Publicity, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Schedules, instructions, maps, ca. 1982 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Vietnam Veterans Parade, Task Force, Minutes, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Vietnam Wing Dedication, KIA lists, nd (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Vietnam Wing Dedication, Lists, Guests, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Vietnam Wing Dedication, Misc. records, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Vietnam Wing Dedication, Photographs, Black and white (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
- Vietnam Wing Dedication, Photographs, Color, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Vietnam Wing Dedication, Video, PSA: Gov. Charles Robb National Salute [unreformatted], 1982 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Visitor statistics, 1955-1973 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 10-11)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- War Memorial Commission, Meeting, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Weekly report of the Clerk of the Works, 1954 November-December (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Artifacts, Partial plank from the USS New Jersey (Box 10)
- Artifacts, Canvas pouch (Box 10)
- Artifacts, Strap (Box 10)
- Artifacts, Vietnamese money (Box 10)
- Artifacts, Cartoon (Box 10)
- Artifacts, Spent shell casing (Box 11)
- Artifacts, Lucite block with soil and gravel from Vierville-sur-Mer (Box 12)
- Artifacts, South Vietnamese flag (Box 13)